Guide to the Erasmus Hall Records 1325–1989 (bulk circa 1775–1975) MS 201
New-York Historical Society
- "Archives of Erasmus Hall High School"
  - Erasmus Hall High School—Survey
    - Survey of the land upon which Erasmus Hall High School stands, executed by Homer L. Bartlett, City Surveyor & Civil Engineer, 1896 July (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder EHHS—Survey (1896))
      Linen, 19 x 24".
  - Erasmus Hall High School—Views
    - Photographs and prints of the school and grounds (8x10 or smaller), undated (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy / High School—Views 8x10″ or smaller)
    - Photographs and prints of the school and grounds (larger than 8x10), undated (Offsite-box RC-9b, Folder Erasmus Hall H.S.—Views larger than 8 x 10″)
    - Photographs and prints of the school and grounds (oversize), undated (Offsite-box RC-9b, Folder EHHS—Views (oversized))
    - Postcards, circa 1905–1920 (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—Postcard Views)
      • Postcards, black and white and color, of Erasmus Hall High School. None are dated, but all are ca. 1905–1920. Some show the Flatbush Ave. front of the school before the addition of the Church Ave. wing. One, ca. 1911, shows the school from Ocean Avenue, before E. 21 St. had been cut through.
      • Also, sets of postcards issued for the 125th anniversary, 1912. One set, in color, features views of the pageant; the other set has views of the school, principal, antiques, etc.
    - Color transparencies, circa 1955–1961 (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Erasmus Hall High School—Views)
  - Erasmus Hall High School—Washington Bicentennial Celebration (1932)
    - Printed program and correspondence relating to program entitled "Episodes in the Life of Washington," presented in the Erasmus Hall courtyard, 1932 May 13 (Offsite-box RC-8a, Folder EHHS Pageants—)
  - Erasmus Hall High School—World War I
    - Lists of Erasmus boys in the service, 1917, 1918 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder World War I)
      From the Erasmian, Oct. and Nov. 1917. Also, Christmas card sent in Dec. 1918 to Erasmians who served in the war.
    - Dedication of the memorial tablet to the Erasmus boys who died in the Great War, 1922 February 10 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder EHHS—World War I)
      Printed program, correspondence.
      See also Erasmus Hall High School—Service Flag Dedication.
    - Material relating to Erasmus Hall students and alumni who served in World War I, undated (Offsite-box MS-23)
      Includes correspondence and photographs.
  - Erasmus Hall High School—World War II
    - [Lists of Erasmus students who served in World War II], 1945 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder WWII—including list of Erasmus boys who served)
      • "Erasmians Serve." 16 x 20" poster listing Erasmus Hall students in the service. Dated May 1945.
      • Dutchman, April 20, 1945, listing Erasmus veterans.
      • Slips of paper with names of Erasmus veterans.
    - Correspondence from Erasmus Hall boys in the service, undated (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder WWII—Correspondence from Erasmus boys in the service)
      Most thanking editor of Dutchman for sending copies of Dutchman.
    - [Certificate and citations], 1944, undated (Offsite-box RC-3b, Folder WWII—Citations to EHHS)
      • Certificate recognizing EHHS as a patron of the Veterans of Foreign Wars National Home, Eaton Rapids, Mich., n.d.
      • Citations for meritorious service awarded to EHHS by New York War Fund, 1944.
  - Erasmus News
    - "The Erasmus News," published by the pupils of Erasmus Hall High School, 1916 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      • Vol. 1, no. 1 (Jan. 5, 1916)
      • Vol. 1, no. 3 (Feb. 2, 1916)
  - Erasmus Spirit
    - "The Erasmus Spirit," published by the pupils of Erasmus Hall High School, 1915, 1922–1923 (Offsite-box RC-4b, Folder "The Erasmus Spirit")
      • Complete run, from v. 1, no. 1 (May 4, 1915) through v. 2, no. 13 (Dec. 15, 1915)
      • New series, v. 1, no. 1 (Oct. 30, 1922); v. 2, no. 1 (Nov. 7, 1922); v. 3, no. 1 (Nov. 6, 1923)
  - Erazzmatazz
    - "Erazzmatazz," published by the students of the Erasmus Hall Institute of the Performing Arts, circa 1974 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Music and Art School Publications)
      • one issue, n.d., but ca. 1974.
  - Exchequer
    - "The Exchequer," published by the school savings bank, 1935–1936 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      • Vol. 1, no. 1 (June 1935) [2 copies]
      • Vol. 2, no. 1 (May 1936) [2 copies]
  - Facets
    - "Facets," magazine of the Social Studies Department, 1967, 1973, 1974 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Facets and "Village of Flatbush")
      • "Village of Flatbush," a Facets publication issued in June 1974 [4 copies]
  - Fantasia
    - "Fantasia," newsletter of the Erasmus Hall Institute of Performing Arts, 1973, 1975 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Music and Art School Publications)
      • Vol. 1, no. 2 (Oct. 1973)
      • Vol. 3, no. 1 (Dec. 1975)
  - Fireplace
    - [Material on the original fireplace installed in Erasmus Hall Academy], 1936, undated (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Fireplace)
      The original fireplace installed in Erasmus Hall Academy when it opened in 1787 remained in the old building until about 1906, when it was removed and installed in the principal's office in the new Flatbush Ave. wing of Erasmus Hall High School. The fireplace was returned to the old Academy building when it was restored and re-opened in 1952. Photograph of the fireplace in the Academy in late 19th century, and clipping from The Dutchman, Apr. 3, 1936.
  - Flatbush
    - "Village of Flatbush", 1973 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Facets and "Village of Flatbush")
      A Facets publication issued in the spring of 1973, featuring history and photographs of Flatbush. 16 p. [4 copies]
  - Flatbush—Clubs
    - "Ye Historie of ye Ingleside, 1885–1900", [circa 1900] (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Clubs)
      A history of the Ingleside Club of Flatbush, a literary society of female members.
  - Flatbush—Historic Homes
    - Clarkson Mansion, 1940 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      "Century-Old Clarkson Mansion, Flatbush Landmark, to be Razed," New York Times, _____, 1940.
    - Ditmas Homestead, 1935 September (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      "Old Ditmas Home Awaits City Plans. Historical Society to Map Project for Museum in Flatbush Dwelling," New York Times, Sept. (3?), 1935.
    - Ditmas or Van Nuys Homestead, [1935–1943] (Offsite-box RC-7, Frame Ditmas or Van Nuys Homestead)
      The Ditmas or Van Nuys Homestead, Brooklyn, N.Y. Etching made by William Hicks. W.P.A. Federal Art Project, N.Y.C. 6 x 8", framed to 12 x 13 ½"
    - Lefferts Homestead, after 1919 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      "The Lefferts Mansion." Undated article from unknown periodical (after 1919).
    - Martense-Story Homestead, 1937 May (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      Martense-Story Homestead: "When Does A Woman Cease To Be Sensitive About Her Age?," from Flatbush: Magazine of Flatbush Chamber of Commerce, May 1937. Tells of "Aunt" Rachel Martense, who lived to be 104, and shows photo of the Martense-Story homestead which stood on Flatbush Ave., east side, near Linden Blvd.
    - Melrose Hall, 1924, undated (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      "The Romance of Melrose Hall," program of the play by Jane Dransfield which was presented in the Church House of the Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church, Dec. 4–5, 1924.
      "The Romance of Melrose Hall," program of play by Jane Dransfield (copyright 1908), n.d. This performance may have been given by the Flatbush Boys' Club, whose officers are listed on the last page.
    - Melrose Hall, 1934 May (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
      Snyder, John J. "Melrose Hall, Flatbush's Haunted House," Flatbush: Magazine of Flatbush Chamber of Commerce, May 1934.
    - "Old Flatbush Homes are Disappearing Fast," Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1911 December 24 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Historic Homes)
  - Flatbush—History
    - "Conditions and stipulations on which the proxies of the widow of the late David Provoost have the intention to sell in public auction to the highest bidder.. .", 1659 March 15 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Original 2-page Dutch document)
      "Conditions and stipulations on which the proxies of the widow of the late David Provoost have the intention to sell in public auction to the highest bidder... the here-after mentioned dwellings, yards, and lands situated in and under the jurisdiction of the village Midwout on the Long Island in the New Netherlands.. ."
      Original, two-page document in Dutch, dated March 15, 1659. Accompanied by photostat copy, transliteration, and translation into English.
      Note: The oldest document bearing the ancient name of Flatbush, "Midwout," is a certificate dated Jan. 15, 1658, signed by Domine Polhemus of the Reformed Dutch Church of Flatbush. Therefore, this 1659 document must be one of the earliest extant uses of "Midwout."
    - "Muster Roll of Detached Militia under the command of Capt. Jeremiah Lott in the 2d Battalion or 64th Regiment of N.Y.S. Infantry commanded by Major Frc. Titus... stationed near Fort Green", [1814] (Offsite-box RC-7)
      A listing of the 79 men in the battalion, with rank, date of app't., names present, remarks and alterations since last muster (including one desertion and two AWOLs). All of the names on this 17 x 21 ½" document are of Flatbush families.
    - Strong, Thomas M. History of the Town of Flatbush... (New York: Thomas R. Mercein Jr.), 1842 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Strong. History of Flatbush, 1842)
    - Fisher, Edmund D. Flatbush Past and Present, 1901 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder "Flatbush Past and Present")
      Envelope mentions 2 copies; only 1 present.
    - All Souls Universalist Church. The Church and the Home in the Realm of Light and Air. All Souls Church and Flatbush of To-Day, 1908 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder [Flatbush of To-Day, 1908])
      The title is misleading; this is an excellent history of Flatbush from its beginning, but with emphasis on the development of Flatbush in the period 1890–1908.
    - [Flatbush tercentenary newspaper clippings and photographs], 1952 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush 300th Anniversary material)
      • "The 300th Birthday of Flatbush," Brooklyn Daily Eagle, May 25, 1952. Special section with dozens of photographs, articles.
      • "Flatbush Joins In Celebrating 300th Anniversary this Week," Flatbush Times, v. 1, no. 10 (May 29, 1952).
      • Photographs of the celebration at EHHS, May 28.
    - Midwout Magazine, v. 3, no. 5 (Fall and Winter), 1913–1914 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder John J. Snyder—historical writings on Flatbush)
      Published by John J. Snyder, of Snyder's of Flatbush. Contains interesting historical material and photos relating to Flatbush.
    - "Flatbush Short Stories", 1923–1926 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder John J. Snyder—historical writings on Flatbush)
      Published by John J. Snyder of "Snyder's of Flatbush." Complete set. Interesting historical material and photographs regarding Flatbush.
  - Flatbush—Maps
    - Map of the town of Flatbush, made Nov. 10, 1797 by Jeremiah Lott, 1902 (Oversize large, Folder 3)
      Reproduction certified as accurate by the State Engineer and Surveyor, 1902. 18 x 26". Gift of Herebert [sic] S. Wynkoop, 1912.
      (Originally in Records Case, Drawer 7.)
    - [Land owned by Nicholas Cowenhoven, Garret Martense, and George Garret and Adrian Martense], circa 1800 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      Survey, 7 ½ x 12 ½", showing three adjoining plots of land owned by Nicholas Cowenhoven, Garret Martense, and George Garret and Adrian Martense. There is no identification as to the location of the lots, so Flatbush is only a guess (the lots may have been in Brooklyn). n.d., but ca. 1800.
    - "A Map representing the main Road leading from Brooklyn ferry to the village of Jamaica, and also from the Church in the village of Flatbush to the junction of the said Road", 1807 January 20 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      By J(eremiah) L(ott). The road referred to is Flatbush Avenue. This is the original, handwritten survey.
    - "Map, Town of Flatbush and New Lots, Kings Co., protracted as per survey on 10th November 1797 of Jeremiah Lott... and also as per survey on the 6th of February 1852 by Teunis G. Bergen.. ." (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
    - Ryerson, G. V. S. Map of Town of Flatbush in 1873 (Brooklyn, New York), 1946 (Offsite-box RC-5b, Roll Flatbush—Map (1873))
      "Compliments of the Flatbush Democratic Club." Includes miniature drawings of old Flatbush residences around the border, numbered to correspond to the map.
    - "Map and Profile of the Flatbush & Coney Island Park & Concourse R.R.", 1877 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      This map shows that part of Flatbush Avenue which was in Flatbush, and indicates who owned each parcel of land.
  - Flatbush—Schools
    - "An agreement... between the Flatbush School District and the Flatlands District No. 2, regarding the boundary line", [1843 April 1] / 1870s (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      This is a copy of the original, in the hand of J. L. Zabriskie, probably done in the 1870s.
    - [Receipts], 1867–1873 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Receipts for Flatbush School #1)
      Receipts for expenditures by Flatbush Public School No. 1 (corner Church and Bedford Avenues), 1867–1873. Many are receipts signed by teachers for salary; others are for supplies, furniture, maintenance.
    - "Account Book District No. 1, Flatbush, L.I. J. D. Randolph, Treasurer. 1869 and 1870", 1847–1879 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Public School—Accounts)
      The title on the cover of the notebook containing these records is misleading: this is the account book of the Flatbush public school (known as the "District No. 1" school), Church and Bedford Avenues, from 1847 through 1879, and is a beautiful manuscript, in the writing of the various Treasurers, the earliest being J. V. Schoonmaker.
    - Census: School District No. 1, Flatbush, L. I., 1870 May (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Census of Flatbush School Children 1870)
      A. Wiggins, Esqr. This notebook lists the 749 white and 23 black children in all schools in Flatbush Dist. No. 1. It gives name and age.
    - [Expenses], circa 1870s (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      • Account of expenses of "East Broadway and Locust St. School." Known today as the intersection of Church and Bedford Avenues, this was the site of the public school of Flatbush. The building still there today (1972) was built in 1878 to replace the wooden structure which had occupied the site.
      • Also, expenses of "Rogers Ave. Branch School" and "East N. Y. Ave. Branch School."
      N.d., but ca. 1870s. J. L. Zabriskie's writing.
    - [Registers], circa 1870s (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Register of parents, with number of children they have attending these three schools, n.d.—ca. 1870s:
      • Private school of Miss Jennie McAllis (20 students)
      • Private school of Miss Bainbridge (15 students)
      • Roman Catholic school (80 students)
    - Account book of Flatbush District No. 1 School, 1878–1891 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Public School—Accounts)
      Kept by John L. Zabriskie, with entries dating from 1878 to 1891. These entries occupy only a small portion of the notebook in which they are found; the rest of the pages are blank.
    - Correspondence of Local School Board #38, Brooklyn, New York, 1902–1908 (Offsite-box RC-12, Folder Local School Board #38...)
      This large folder contains reports handed in by the various schools in the district, petitions for new schools, lists of absent teachers, etc. In 1903, this school board was located in "Erasmus Hall High School, Cottage #4, 34 Locust St." This was on the present site of the Bedford Ave. wing.
      There is some correspondence regarding Erasmus Hall High School (petitions for new building), the old P.S. 90, corner of Church and Bedford Avenues, and the new P.S. 139, at "Avenue C and 15th Street" (Cortelyou Rd. and Rugby Road).
      There is also a letter of introduction for Willis Boughton, English teacher at Erasmus Hall, who was an applicant for position of assistant in English at the College of the City of New York (1903).
    - Glenwood Road School, 1908 June 12 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Public Schools)
      The Glenwood Road School: Public School No. 152, Glenwood Road and East 23rd Street, Brooklyn, New York. Dedication and Presentation Exercises Under the Auspices of the South Midwood Residents' Association, Friday, June the Twelfth, 1908. Printed program with photograph of the school.
    - Snyder, John J. "The Flatbush Village School," (reprinted from) Flatbush Magazine, 1938 September (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder John J. Snyder—historical writings on Flatbush)
      Gives a history of the Flatbush public school from 1659 to date. Includes a full history of the school which stood on the corner of Church and Bedford Aves.
    - [Letters to Principal John F. McNeill], 1957 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Public Schools)
      Letters to Dr. John F. McNeill (EHHS principal) from Borough President John Cashmore and Board of Education Assistant Supt. David H. Moskowitz, regarding the building known as P.S. 90 originally the Flatbush public school, at Church and Bedford Avenues. The letters, dated 1957, relate to McNeill's efforts to procure the building as an annex.
  - Flatbush—Schools—Library
    - [Correspondence regarding transfer of District School No. 1 Library to Erasmus Hall], [1897] (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder EHHS Library—Museum)
      The library of the old public school of the town of Flatbush (known as School District No. 1, Town of Flatbush, Kings Co.) was, by vote of the trustees of the school district, transferred in 1897 to Erasmus Hall High School. Correspondence between Walter B. Gunnison, EHHS principal, and John Z. Lott, trustee of the school district, relating to the transfer.
    - "Catalogue of Library in Public School No. 1, Flatbush, L. I.", 1893 October (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Catalogue of Library in Public School No. 1)
  - Flatbush—Streets
    - [Receipt for flagstone laid on Wyckoff Street], 1846 July 1 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      "Brooklyn 1 July 1846. Mrsesses. Sullivan & Cotter, to Peter Lynan to 284 feet 8 inches of flagging liad (sic-laid) in front of thare [sic] yard in Wyckoff Street... $25.62. Recd payment (signed) Peter Lynan."
    - Petition and correspondence relating to the closing of Ocean Avenue, 1878 January 22 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      • Petition and correspondence relating to the closing of Ocean Avenue at its intersection with Clarkson St. by the Rail Road Company, which was constructing a line from the City Line to Coney Island. Presented by Miss Louise G. Zabriskie.
      • In addition to the petition, dated Jan. 22, 1878, and addressed to the Commissioners of Highways of Flatbush, are letters from various lawyers concerned.
  - Flatbush—Views
    - Collection of miscellaneous photographs of old Flatbush (and some Flatlands) homes [NOT PRESENT], undated (Box [unknown])
      Most are unidentified. n.d., but most are late 19th cent.
      Recorded as being in Drawer 6.
    - "Sketch of Labon's Inn, Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn, 1853, taken by A. L. Vanderbilt, City Surveyor", 1865 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Views)
      For Henry McClosky's Manual, 1865. Lithograph, uncolored, 9 x 11", poor condition.
    - Postcard album of views of Flatbush, circa 1900 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Postcard album of Flatbush)
      Consisting primarily of post cards issued by F. A. Lippold, Flatbush, N.Y.
    - Postcard album with post cards of the old homesteads and beautiful homes of Flatbush, circa 1905 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Postcard album of Flatbush)
      These postcards are nearly all c. 1905, and most are from the high-quality series produced by F. A. Lippold of Flatbush. The album belonged to Charlotte S. Vanderbilt of 598 Flatbush Ave., Flatbush.
    - Committee to Preserve Flatbush Town Hall plaques, 1972 December (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Plaques of Historic Flatbush)
      Set of five plaques issued by the Committee to Preserve Flatbush Town Hall in December 1972. The following landmarks are shown: Reformed Dutch Church, Wyckoff-Bennett Homestead, Wyckoff-House, Flatbush Town Hall, and Lefferts Homestead.
  - Flatbush—Voters
    - "Register of Voters in the Election District in the Town of Flatbush, 1859" (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Voters)
      7 ½ x 12" notebook with mss. list of the voters in Flatbush in 1859. Signed by the inspectors of election, J. V. Schoonmaker, John J. Vanderbilt, and Abraham Lott. (Probably a gift of Mr. F. J. H. Kracke; see card for Flatbush—Voters—1860)
    - "Register of Electors in the Election District in the Town of Flatbush, 1860" (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush—Voters)
      7 ½ x 12" notebook with mss. list of the voters in Flatbush in 1860. Signed by the inspectors of election, J. V. Schoonmaker, John Lefferts, and John J. Vanderbilt. Note inserted inside front cover: "gift of Mr. F. J. H. Kracke."
  - Flatbush Highway Commission
    - Minutes and petition, 1872, 1873 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      • Minutes of meeting held April 8, 1872 at Schoonmaker Hall, in the hand of John L. Zabriskie, secretary.
      • Petition to the Commissioners, dated May 21, 1872, from "residents and owners of real estate fronting on Grant street between Prospect street and Nostrand Ave. in the town of Flatbush," complaining that "after every rain and snow storm large ponds of water remain on said street for a long time thereafter, and that the stench arising from the same is very offensive and injurious.. ." (Note: Grant Street is now known as Snyder Avenue.) The petition is signed by twelve individuals.
      • Minutes of meeting held April 7, 1873. "Resolved, that proposal to invite (bids) for painting the street lamps from the painters in the Town to be presented at the next meeting of the board." Written by J. L. Zabriskie.
    - Petition and correspondence, 1878 (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      Petition and correspondence relating to the closing of Ocean Avenue at its intersection with Clarkson Street by the Rail Road Co., which was constructing a line from the City Line to Coney Island. Presented by Miss Louise G. Zabriskie.
      In addition to the petition (dated Jan. 22, 1878), which is addressed to the Commissioners of Highways of Flatbush, are letters from various parties concerned.
  - Flatbush of To-Day
    - All Souls Universalist Church. Flatbush of To-Day, 1908 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder [Flatbush of To-Day, 1908])
      Excellent source for history of the old families and landmarks of Flatbush.
  - FLATBUSH: Published by the Flatbush Nostrand Chambers of Commerce, Inc.
    - Bicentennial Issue, 1976 June 19 (Offsite-box RC-15, Item FLATBUSH: Published by the Flatbush Nostrand...)
  - Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church
    - Miscellaneous clippings, programs, and brochures, undated (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church)
    - [Stained glass windows], circa 1889 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church)